Guide to the International Union of Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers, Local 485 Records WAG.137
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
International Union of Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers, Local 485 Records
1938-1992
1955-1985
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
International Union of Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers. Local 485
WAG.137
6 Linear Feet in 4 record cartons and 4 manuscript box.
Chartered by the Congress of Industrial Organizations in 1935-1936, the United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America (UE) quickly became one of the "big three" CIO unions. Local 475 was chartered in June 1939 as a merger of three UE locals, all involved in organizing small manufacturing concerns. With the outbreak of WWII and the expansion of war-related manufacturing, Local 475's organizing efforts were successful. Contracts were negotiated with 100 shops, most of them in Brooklyn, and the local grew to 20,000 members. The UE withdrew from the CIO under threat of expulsion in 1949, and in 1956 Local 475 entered the recently formed International Union of Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers (IUE), becoming Local 485. This collection includes minutes of the Stewards Council, Executive Board and general membership meetings of Local 485 and its predecessor Local 475; information on union elections, conventions, and financial reports; as well as materials pertaining to other locals and special events. The Local's extensive bargaining and arbitration history is well represented. The collection also includes fifty photographs and a small amount of ephemera.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials found in repository; provenance is unknown. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 1987.002, 1987.008, and NPA.2006.012.
Arrangement
Series I is arranged chronologically. Series II, IV and V are arranged alphabetically by topic and Series III is arranged alphabetically by employer.
The collection is arranged into five series:
Series I: Minutes, 1946-1977
Series II: General Files, 1939-1986
Series III: Bargaining Files, 1938-1988
Series IV: Arbitration Files, 1949-1979
Series V: Photographs, circa 1942-1992
Historical Note
Chartered by the Congress of Industrial Organizations in 1935-1936, the United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America (UE) quickly became one of the "big three" CIO unions. Local 475 was chartered in June 1939 as a merger of three UE locals: Local 1230 representing employees of the International Projector Corporation in Manhattan, organized in 1937 by Charles Fay who became the longtime president of Local 475 and its successor; Local 1222 representing Morgenthaler employees, dating back to the mid-1930s; and Local 1223, formerly a Machinists local which had been organized at Eissman in the early 1930s. The merger was engineered to combine the strength of the three locals, all involved in organizing small manufacturing concerns. With the outbreak of WWII and the expansion of war-related manufacturing, Local 475's organizing efforts were successful. Contracts were negotiated with 100 shops, most of them in Brooklyn, and the local grew to 20,000 members. The UE withdrew from the CIO under threat of expulsion in 1949, and in 1956 Local 475 entered the recently formed International Union of Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers (IUE), becoming Local 485.
Scope and Content Note
This collection includes minutes of the Stewards Council, Executive Board and general membership meetings of Local 485 and its predecessor Local 475. Subject files contain information on union elections, conventions and financial reports; other United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America (UE) and International Union of Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers (IUE) locals; as well as materials pertaining to social and other special events. The Local's extensive bargaining and arbitration history is well represented. The collection also includes fifty photographs documenting a 1967 IUE convention, strikes in 1951 and 1979 and other events. A small amount of ephemera includes fliers, certificates, newsletters and an IUE cap.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access to some audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Leaflets (printed works); Reports.; Minutes (administrative records); Printed ephemera.; Collective bargaining -- New York (State) -- New York.; Machinists -- Labor unions; Electric industry workers -- Labor unions -- United States.; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Arbitration, Industrial -- New York (State) -- New York.; Negatives (photographic); Photographs.; United Electrical, Radio and Machine Workers of America; Fay, Charles
- Series I: Minutes, 1946-1977
  - Stewards Council, Executive Board, and Membership Meetings, 1946-1947 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Stewards Council, Executive Board, and Membership Meetings, 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Membership Meetings, 1958-1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Executive Board, 1957-1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Executive Board, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Executive Board and Shop Chairman, 1969-1977 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series II: General Files, 1939-1986
  - Activities Bulletin, 1957-1960 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Allen Co., 1966 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Amalgamated Locals, 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Archer, Hamilton, 1968-1971 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Badillo, Herman, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Briggs, Ernest, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Cameron, Clifton, 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Classes, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Committees (list), 1961 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Constitution, 1963-1964 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Convention, 1956, 1958, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Convention, 1963, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Convention, 1969, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Credit Union, 1956-1960 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Cutroneo, Leo, 1968-1969 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Dances, 1953-1963 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Delegates Manual (Spanish), 1953 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Dynamos, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Elections, 1956-1966 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Elections, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Elections, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Elections, 1971, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Elections (UER and MWA), 1947-1948 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Employers (research), 1957-1958 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Eton Silver, inc, 1958-1976 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Executive Committee Report, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Fay, Charles, 1942-1969 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Financial Reports, 1956-1959 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Financial Reports, 1960-1964 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Financial Reports, 1965-1969 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Financial Reports, 1970-1977 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Form Letters, 1966-1969 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Health and Welfare Fund, 1959-1979 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Human Rights/Civil Rights, 1940-1967 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Internal Security: Investigations, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Investigation Committee, 1967-1970 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - International Union of Electrical Workers, 1956-1973 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - International Union of Electrical Workers, District 3, 1963-1983 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - International Union of Electrical Workers, District 4, 1956-1963 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - International Union of Electrical Workers, District 4: Defection from Union of Electrical Workers, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - International Union of Electrical Workers, Local 133, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - International Union of Electrical Workers, Local 450, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Jamco Manufacturing Corp., 1978 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Jayar Metal Finishing Corp., 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Job Calls, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Job Descriptions, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Job Descriptions (I), 1946-1957 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Job Descriptions (II), 1946-1957 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Labor Council for Latin American Advancement, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Leaflets, 1967-1971 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Legislative/Political, 1957-1973 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Manley, Nat: Spanish Lessons, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - March on Washington, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Membership Meetings, 1959-1966 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Mineworkers, Support for, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Model Clauses and Contracts, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Nigris, Mike, 1968-1970 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - National Labor Relations Board Cases, 1967-1975 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Parades, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - "Party" Document (CP?), undated (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Play: "A Local Grows in Brooklyn", 1960 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Powell, Adam Clayton, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Romans, Angel, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Salguero, Joe, 1967-1969 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Seniority Rosters, 1940-1957 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Shop Meetings, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Shop Newspapers, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Simplex Equipment Shop, 1957-1958 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Skilled Trades, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Songs/Poems, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Sperry Locals (Local 450), 1957 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Sperry Strike, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Staff, 1957-1963 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Stagg Zipper Corp., 1964-1975 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Stewards Meetings, 1956-1957 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Supreme Court Case: Joseph Markovits, inc., 1957 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Torres, Santiago, 1970-1986 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Tubular Cast, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Tung-Sol Workers, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - United Electrical Workers, 1946-1957 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - United Electrical Workers, Local 475, 1939-1955 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - United Electrical Workers, Local 475: Anti-Discrimination, 1953-1955 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - United Electrical Workers: Till Murder Case, 1955 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Yauco Civic and Social Club, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- Series III: Bargaining Files, 1938-1988
  - Acme Brass, 1968-1973 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Aerosol Machine Corporation, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Aljen Manufacturing Corporation, 1968-1973 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Aljon Finishing Corporation, 1967-1976 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Altman Stage and Lighting Company, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - A & L Tool and Stamping Company, 1970-1982 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Apex Metal Stamping Company, 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Arrow Lock Corporation, 1963-1983 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Ateco Manufacturing Company, 1970-1988 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Automotive Plating Corporation, 1960-1974 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Bayside Watch and Tool Company, 1970-1986 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Beaver Polishing and Plant Corporation, 1966-1982 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Burndy Corporation, 1967-1976 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Cello Company, 1972-1976 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Century Aluminum, 1962-1965 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Century Projector Corporation, 1968-1978 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Chelsea Pen Incorporated, 1968-1974 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Circle Air Industries, 1962-1967 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Columbia Surgical Industry Corporation, 1969-1975 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Crown Die Casting Corporation, 1969-1984 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Cutting Tools Incorporated, 1969-1986 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Dash Metal Products, 1968-1977 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Dominion Vinyl Corporation, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Duralite Company, 1959 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - D.W. Haber and Son, 1968-1990 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Electri-Cord Manufacturing Company, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Emery Thompson Machine and Supply Company, 1971-1982 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Excelsior Pen, 1961 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Federal Pump Corporation, 1964-1985 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Federal Pump Repair Company, 1970-1985 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Federal Silver Company, 1961-1962 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Ferdinand Gutmann & Company, 1966-1984 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - Fisher Scientific Company, 1960-1968 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - F.L. Smithe Machine Company, 1960-1966 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Forman Family, 1968-1983 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Garber Packing Corporation, 1970-1976 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - General Floor Craft, 1964-1985 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Globe Plating Company, 1968-1987 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Grillion Corporation (Formerly Jaffre Manufacturing Corporation), 1969-1981 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Heldor Manufacturing Company, 1963 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Howmedica, 1971-1985 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - International Projector Corporation, 1938-1957 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Jamco Manufacturing Corporation & Safeguard Manufacturing Corporation, 1979-1981 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Jelrus Technical Products Corporation, 1966-1985 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - J.H.H. Voss Company, 1949-1968 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - J. Sklar Manufacturing Company, 1969-1984 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Juliart Lamp Manufacturing Company, 1970-1988 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Julie Pomerantz and Company, 1968-1972 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - King's Automatic Corporation, 1968-1977 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Klett Manufacturing Company, 1968-1986 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Krischner Metal Products, 1968-1983 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - La Belle Silver Company, 1962-1964 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Lafayette Grinding Corporation, 1969-1986 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Lafayette Saw and Knife Corporation, 1972-1984 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - La Montre Watch Case Company, 1982 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Lehman Brothers Silverware Corporation, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Lenkay Sani Products Corporation, 1970-1983 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Lincoln Machine Parts Company, 1970-1983 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Lion Machine Corporation, 1961-1970 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Lof and Sons, 1968-1983 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Manhattan Gear and Instrument Company, 1961-1965 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Marmike Manufacturing Corporation, 1961-1965 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Miller-Charles Company, 1972-1983 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Molla Incorporated, 1967-1982 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - National Tin Can Manufacturing Corporation, 1969-1979 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Rex Electra Manufacturing Corporation, 1961-1963 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Roberts Brass Incorporated, 1962-1964 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Rowe Industries, 1969-1971 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Saf Manufacturing Company, 1968-1970 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Sanitary Dash Corporation, 1955 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Selectro Plating Company, 1968-1983 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Signal-Stat Corporation, 1963-1977 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Simplex Cloth Cutting Machine, 1969-1982 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Singer Supreme Company, 1959-1966 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Slant Fin Corporation, 1956-1986 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Stagg Zipper, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Talon, Division of Textron Incorporated, 1968-1980 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Van Buren Machine Corporation, 1956-1964 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Vinyl Masters Incorporated, 1965-1984 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Woodhaven Metal Stamping Company, 1969-1984 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Zimmer Manufacturing Corporation, 1966-1980 (Box 5, Folder 40)
- Series IV: Arbitration Files, 1949-1976
  - Automotive Plating, 1964-1973 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Back Pay, 1951-1952 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Bargaining Unit, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Cromwell Silver Corporation, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Distribution of Overtime, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Downgrading, 1950-1963 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Dues Check-Off, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Dues Delinquency, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Eveready Hardware Manufacturing Company, 1956-1959 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Firings, 1949-1968 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Grievance Procedures, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Group Insurance, 1949-1963 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Holiday Pay, 1949-1964 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Improper Job Application, 1949-1960 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Incentive, 1954-1955 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - International Projector Corporation, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Job Classifications Establishment, 1963 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Lay-Offs, 1949-1964 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Merit Increases, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Plant Visitation, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Premium Pay, 1962-1965 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Progression Pay, 1951-1956 (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Re-Classification, 1948-1982 (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Re-Hiring, 1949-1958 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Roberto Portuondo, 1968 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - S & S Sheet Metal, 1965 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Seniority, 1949-1968 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Severance Pay, 1949-1963 (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Sick Leave Pay, 1961-1976 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Sub-Contracting, 1949-1950 (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Suspensions, 1954-1962 (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Vacations, 1948-1964 (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Wage Questions, 1947-1961 (Box 6, Folder 33)
  - Warnings, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 34)
  - Working Foremen, 1951-1955 (Box 6, Folder 35)
- Series V: Photographs and Ephemera, circa 1942-1992
  - Arrow Lock Strike, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Convention, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - Duralite Strike, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - Ephemera, circa 1942-1992 (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - General Photographs, 1947-1951; undated (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Negatives, undated (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Oversize Ephemera (Includes United Farm Workers), 1966; undated (Box Shared Tamiment MSOS006, Folder 1)
- Series VI: Media
  - Films, cuid15020 (Box 7, Box 8)
  - UE Local 475 Banquet, undated; cuid15021_A (Box Shared Tamiment 166, Reel cuid15021_A)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Format: 16mm
  - IUE Local 485 Event, undated; cuid15021_B (Box Shared Tamiment 133, 16mm film reels cuid15021_B)